Let's talk about something nobody wants
to talk about. Bioeththics. Please prove
me wrong that no one wants to hear it.
You can take human stem cells and create
chimeas with animals. There's even been
reports that some neural chimeas that
means mice that have human brain tissue
that was inserted during their fetal
stage ends up more intelligent. You
actually can replace a pretty
significant portion of a mouse's brain
with human stem cells. And that is very
important. We finally have the ability
to study human conditions. how human
cells communicate without working with
an actual human, which should be more
ethical. Except here's where the big
problems come in. I included really like
the spooky aspects of science, but
somehow I've ended up being a science
communicator and I have extra
responsibilities. When we personify
things like chimeas, we want to give
them extra rights for being partly
human. When we personify the tiny human
brains that you can grow in a literal
jar and have run computation, it does
end up freaking people out. Now,
Cortical Labs, one of the two companies
where you can use brain organoids at a
distance to do your computation. They
were the ones who claimed sentience in a
dish. They were highly criticized in the
scientific community for making such
extraordinary claims. Why? Because
sentience is a very difficult thing to
actually demonstrate the capacity to
have an experience. Saying so without a
unified way to define the term does end
up making brain organoid research a
little bit more difficult to do. This
can end up being very valuable research.
It's extraordinarily valuable for the
same reason chimeas are valuable because
you can do actual research on human
tissues without the person. This is
actually the same reason why colossal
biosciences lost my respect because they
didn't actually make dire wolves. They
made wolves with dog jeans to be really
big. But making big claims gets funding.
That's part of the problem. When we
personify science, we're committing the
marological fallacy. The idea that the
parts are the same as the whole, which
they're not. While the really spooky and
exciting claims are exciting, I hope we
get conscious robots one day, they can
end up hindering the field as a whole.
You think you know something about
people who don't entirely understand
what you're working with and want to
stop you because somebody presented it
as scary. Yes, that's a pretty big
problem in science. Let's look at some
research highlights. Researchers have
been able to model Alzheimer's disease
in mice using human neurons, embriionic
stem cells. This means that we may get
closer to a treatment because
medications can be tested on human cells
just not humans. and having them in a
living model shows us how they actually
behave, not just cells on a plate.
Albeit they are behaving with mouse
cells. So they may not be 100% the same,
but we are able to give mice conditions
that otherwise humans would get. Also, I
just really want to tell people this,
but there's no evidence that human head
transplantation is going to be a thing.
There are papers examining the ethics of
it despite that it doesn't appear to be
a thing or ever going to be a thing.
I've looked at a lot of papers on how
people want to try to carry it out. I'm
so sorry. It's just not happening. I
never wanted to be people's sole source
of human brain organoid or biological
horror information, but somehow I've
become that and now I feel I have a
greater responsibility to tell the
truth. Although I love the spooky sides
of things, I just got to be honest with
y'all. I care. I I actually do care. And
if people shut down the research, how
will we ever get conscious robots?